A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series V: Engravings, Prints, Photographs
  - Walt Whitman, [ca. 1870], 1 8x10 copy, 1 item, Saunders #31, #3829-s. (Box-folder 4:69)
    Photograph by G. Frank Pearsall, Brooklyn. Original signed, "Walt Whitman Jan 1-1878".
  - Walt Whitman, [early 1870's], 2 items, Saunders #39, #3829-h. (Box-folder 4:70)
    Photograph by J. Gurney and Son, New York.
    c.1: Mounted image, "Gurney & Son, Fifth Ave. N. Y."
    c.2: Copy, with typed description on verso: "Hitherto unpublished photograph of Walt Whitman from the private collection of Robert Coster. This is the only photograph of Whitman known to be in existence."
  - Walt Whitman, 1871, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #34. #3829-a. (Box-folder 4:71)
    Photograph by Henry Ulke and Brothers, Washington D. C. Inscribed on verso: "Presented to Mr. [C. O. Maillong ?] by Mrs. Mary O. Davis May 20th 1903."
  - Walt Whitman, [1871?], 1 item, mounted, Saunders #41, #3829-h. (Box-folder 4:72)
    Recto: "Rockwood 1440 Broadway, N.Y. (40th St.) Holland Building. Verso: Inscribed, "Walt Whitman," in unknown hand.
  - Walt Whitman, [1871?], 1 item, mounted. #3829-a. (Box-folder 4:73)
    Inscribed in pencil on verso: "Turney & Son Photographers." After careful scrutiny of image, although extremely similar to Saunders #41, there is slight discrepancy which indicates a different image.
  - Walt Whitman, [1871?], 1 print from wood engraving, mounted, Saunders #44a, #3829-x. (Box-folder 4:74)
    Print by William J. Linton from a photograph of George C. Potter, Washington, D.C., with three copies.
  - Caricature of Walt Whitman, 1872, 1 print, #3829-i. (Box-folder 4:75)
    From "Men of the Day," the Fifth Avenue Journal, (copy # 89 out of 100). Original in Vault oversize V-13.
  - Walt Whitman, [1872 September], Signed, 4 copies, Saunders #36, #3829-i, #3829-v. (Box-folder 5:1)
    #3829-v, Gift in honor of Floyd Stovall. Photograph by G. Frank Pearsall, Brooklyn.
    c.1. Photograph signed by Walt Whitman, "Walt Whitman 1877"
    c. 2. Photograph signed by Walt Whitman, "Walt Whitman"
    c. 3. Mounted photograph, without printed caption at bottom
    c. 4. Mounted photograph, with printed caption at bottom: "Photo'd from life, Sept., '72, Brooklyn, N.Y. by G. F. E. Pearsall, Fulton St. (Printed by C. F. Spieler, Phila.)
    c. 5. Mounted double photograph, without caption [possibly a stereoview]
  - Walt Whitman, 1872, 1 item, Saunders #32, #3829-t. (Box-folder 5:2)
    Photograph by G. Frank Pearsall, Brooklyn.
  - Walt Whitman, 1876, 1 item, #3829-v. (Box-folder 5:2A)
    Wood engraving of a portrait by Linton, 1875, with a proof title page of the 1876 edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - Walt Whitman, 1878, 2 copies, mounted, Saunders #37.1, #3829-v, #3829-j. (Box-folder 5:3)
    #3829-v, Gift in honor of Floyd Stovall. Photograph by Napoleon Sarony, New York, with two copies.
    c.1. Photograph signed by Walt Whitman, "Walt Whitman Sept 13 1881"
    c.2 Photograph, mounted, unsigned.
  - Walt Whitman, 1878, 1 print, #9714. (Box-folder 5:4)
    Etching by [Gribayedoff?], based on 1878 photograph by Napoleon Sarony.
  - Walt Whitman, 1878, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #57, #5604. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Photograph by Napoleon Sarony, New York, [?] 87 Union Square, N. Y.
  - Walt Whitman, 1878, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #64, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:6)
    Photograph by Napoleon Sarony, New York.
  - Walt Whitman, 1878, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #89, #3829-a. (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Walt Whitman with two children, 1879, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #68, #3829-i. (Box-folder 5:8)
    Inscribed "Harry and Kitty-Walt Whitman, 1879." Enclosed in John H. Johnston letter to Mr. Watson, March 11, 1912.
  - Walt Whitman with two children, 1879, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #67, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:9)
    Inscribed on verso, "Harold, 'Kittie', and 'Uncle Walt,'" by William Kurtz, New York, Madison Square.
  - Walt Whitman with child (Harold Johnston), 2 copies, mounted, Saunders #69, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:10)
    Photograph by William Kurtz, New York.
    c.1: grass drawn into child's hand, no inscription. Inscribed on verso: Loaned by Bertha Johnston 389 Clinton St. Brooklyn.
    c.2: grass drawn into child's hand, with inscription from "Leaves of Grass" on bottom, "'a child said to me "What is the grass?" fetching it to me with full hands. How could I answer the child!'" Inscribed on verso: "Miss Bertha Johnston 514-8" [...] Brooklyn. Walt Whitman, Harry Johnston (Harold Hugh)"
  - Walt Whitman, [1880], 1 post card, Saunders #74, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:11)
    Original photograph by Edy Brothers, London Ontario.
  - Walt Whitman, 1880, 1 6x8 copy with touch-up, Saunders #75, #3829-i. (Box-folder 5:12)
    Original photograph by Edy Brothers, London, Ontario. Stamped "Walt Whitman" on verso.
  - Walt Whitman, 1880, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #76, #3829-v. (Box-folder 5:13)
    Gift in honor of Floyd Stovall. Photograph by Edy Brothers, London, Ontario, with two copies.
  - Walt Whitman, 1880, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #80, #3829-a, #3829-i, #3829-v. (Box-folder 5:14)
    #3829-v, Gift in honor of Floyd Stovall.
    c.1: Printed on bottom of phototype: "Photoype. F. Gutekunst. Philadelphia."
    c.2: Image by Thomas C. Watkins, originally enclosed with AMS draft "The Dalliance of Eagles."
    c.3: Mounted phototype, printed at bottom, "Phototype. F. Gutekunst. Philadelphia."
    c.4: Inscribed on verso: "Presented to Dr. Raley H. Bell by Mrs. Mary O. Davis. May 20th 1903."
  - Walt Whitman, [1880?], 1 item, mounted, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:15)
    Photographer unknown, perhaps Edy Brothers, London, Ontario. Printed on verso: "Broadbent & Taylor 914 Chestnut St. Philadelphia. S. Broadbent. W. Curtis Taylor."
  - Walt Whitman, 1881, 1 item, #3829. (Box-folder 5:16)
    Inscribed on verso, "made by Gutekunst 1881-early copy given to H.T. by W.W.,"
  - Walt Whitman, [1881?], 1 item, mounted, Saunders #101. #3829-a. (Box-folder 5:17)
    By Charles H. Spieler, Philadelphia.
  - Walt Whitman, [1881?], 1 item, mounted, Saunders #102. #3829-a. (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Walt Whitman seated in chair with butterfly, early 1880's, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #48, #3829-a. (Box-folder 5:19)
    Photograph by Phillips and Taylor, Philadelphia. Inscribed on back: "Presented to Raley H. Bell by Mrs. Mary O. Davis May 20th 1908."
  - Walt Whitman, 1887, 1 print, Saunders #80, #3829-i. (Box-folder 5:20)
    Based on 1880 Frederick Gutekunst photograph. Printed below image: "Walt Whitman, 1887."
  - Walt Whitman, 1887, 2 prints, mounted, Saunders #93, #3829-h, #3829-i. (Box-folder 5:21)
    Photograph by George C. Cox, New York.
    c.1. signed print.
    c.2. unsigned print.
  - Walt Whitman seated in rocking chair, 1887, 2 copies, mounted, Saunders #96, #3829-h, #3829-i. (Box-folder 5:22)
    Photograph by Frank P. Harned, Camden.
    c.1: Signed photograph, "Walt Whitman"
    c.2: Unsigned photograph. Inscribed on verso: "To J H Johnston Camden NJ Feb 24 1893 Taken in Camden by F. P. Harned about 188[9?]"
  - Walt Whitman, 1887, 1 6x9 copy, #3829-s. (Box-folder 5:23)
    Photographer unknown, probably Frank P. Harned, Camden (similar to Saunders #96).
  - Walt Whitman, [1887?], 1 item, #3829-y. (Box-folder 5:24)
    Photographer unknown, probably George C. Cox. Image similar to Saunders #98.
  - Walt Whitman, 1887, 1 item, signed, mounted, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:25)
    Inscribed on verso: "Given to me by Mary Davis Mar 27 1895 J H Johnston." Photographer unknown, probably Thomas Eakins, Philadelphia.
  - Walt Whitman, 1888?, 1 item, mounted, Saunders #100, #3829-a. (Box-folder 5:26)
    Photograph possibly by Frederick Gutekunst, Philadelphia.
  - [Walt Whitman?] with unidentified girl, 1889, 1 5x6 copy, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:27)
    Photograph by H. C. Willets. More than likely an early hoax photograph. Biographical note of Walt Whitman top left. Printed below: "This is a photo enlarged from a Kodak 3x4 in a form never before in print and some facts never before made."
  - Walt Whitman, 1889, 2 copies, mounted, Saunders #112, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:28)
    Original signed, "Walt Whitman in 1890." Photograph by Frederick Gutekunst, Philadelphia.
  - Walt Whitman, 1890 May 31, 1 pencil sketch, #5604. (Box-folder 5:29)
    Pencil sketch by Joseph Jackson, inscribed on verso, "sketched at Reisser's at the Walt Whitman dinner. Jo Jackson May 31, 1890," with explanatory letter, July 28, 1943, from Joseph Jackson to Mr. Borneman regarding sketch.
  - Walt Whitman, 1890, 1 silhouette, signed, #3829-b. (Box-folder 5:30)
    Inscribed: "Walt Whitman, Camden, N. J. 1890-cut from life by his friend B. D."
  - Walt Whitman, [1891], 1 copper engraving plate, Saunders #95, #3829-h, #10602. (Box-folder 5:31)
    Copper plate for engraving by T. E. Johnson, based on 1887 George C. Cox photograph. Original copper plate and framed print in Vault-Barrett-Oversize W-5. 71 strikes from copper engraving plate in Vault-Barrett-Oversize V-13.
  - Walt Whitman, 1920, 1 etching, mounted, #10602. (Box-folder 5:32)
    Etching completed as a bust framed with classical motifs, with a reproduction of his signature framed below by Bernhardt Wall.
  - "Walt Whitman, 1819-1892," 1955 April 19 and March 22, 2 invitations, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:33)
    Invitations from the Grolier Club to the Walt Whitman exhibit, with enclosure.
  - "Walt," an abstract portrait of Walt Whitman, [1957 May 6], 1 print. (Box-folder 5:34)
    Painting by Carl Holty. "Walt" by permission of Mr. Holty and Addison Gallery of American Art, Phillips Academy.
  - Photograph Album containing 17 photographs of Walt Whitman and 1 photograph of Mark Twain, n.d., 1 item, #3829-t. (Box-folder 5:35)
    Images attached to leaves of notebook
    p.1: Walt Whitman, 1866. Saunders #23.1
    p.2: Walt Whitman, [1867?]. Saunders 24
    p.3: Walt Whitman, 1866. Saunders #23.1
    p.4: Walt Whitman, 1880. Saunders #76.
    p.5: Walt Whitman, ca. 1862. Saunders #16
    p.6: Walt Whitman, [1867?]. Saunders #24
    p.6a: Walt Whitman, 1866. Saunders #23.1
    p.7: Walt Whitman, [1869?]. Saunders #70
    p.7a: Walt Whitman, 1866. Saunders #23.1
    p.8: Walt Whitman, [1881?]. Saunders #101
    p.9: Walt Whitman, 1887. Saunders #98
    p.9: Walt Whitman, ca. 1862. Saunders #16
    p.10: Walt Whitman, [1869?]. Saunders #70
    p.11: Walt Whitman, 1887. Saunders #94.
    p.12: Mark Twain
    p.12a: Walt Whitman, 1887. Saunders #92.
    p.13: Walt Whitman, 1887. Saunders #95.
    p.14: Walt Whitman, 1878. Saunders #71
  - Walt Whitman, n.d., 1 ink sketch, framed, #3829-t. (Box-folder 5:36)
    Sketch by Joseph Simpson.
  - Walt Whitman, n.d., 1 pen-and-ink sketch, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:37)
    Sketch by George W. Waters. Printed below: "Pen-and-ink sketch of Walt Whitman by George W. Waters, of Elmira, New York, given by him to Mrs. Alma Calder Johnston, in whose New York home both poet and artist were frequent guests."
  - Walt Whitman, by G.M. Ottinger. [1879], 1 painting, Saunders #37.1, #10602. (Box-folder 5:38)
    Possibly based on 1878 Napoleon Sarony photograph of Walt Whitman.
  - Walt Whitman, n.d., 1 crayon drawing, #3829. (Box-folder 5:39)
    Drawing by Eastman Johnson.
  - Walt Whitman, n.d., 1 woodcut print, #7267. (Box-folder 5:40)
    Original woodcut by Antonio Frasconi.
  - Walt Whitman, n.d., 1 print, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:41)
    Artist unknown.
  - Walt Whitman, n.d., 1 print, #3829-w. (Box-folder 5:42)
    From the Painting by J. W. Alexander," by Kurtz. Published in H arpers Magazine, volume 84, Number 503, April 1892.
  - Miscellaneous clippings: Four portraits of Walt Whitman, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 5:43)
    Includes:
    Portrait of Walt Whitman by Thomas Eakins
    Photograph of Walt Whitman, 1889, Saunders #111
    Portrait of Walt Whitman painted from life by Mr. John W. Alexander
    Photograph of Walt Whitman and Warren Fritzinger, 1890, Saunders #108, with caption: "Whitman on the Wharf at Camden, N.J."
  - "Walt Whitman Birthplace, Huntington Station," [1959-1960], 1 printed item. (Box-folder 5:44)
    From cover of Suffolk Telephone Directory.
  - Walt Whitman's birth place, n.d., 1 painting, mounted, #3829-h. (Box-folder 5:45)
  - Walt Whitman's residence, n.d., 2 photographs, #3829-s. (Box-folder 5:46)
    1. Interior of Walt Whitman's room. Verso: "Life Photo by Herbert Gehr"
    2. Photograph of outside plaque. Verso: "Life Photo by Herbert Gehr"
  - Walt Whitman statue, n.d., 2 photographs, #3829-s. (Box-folder 5:47)
    Verso of both photographs: "Credit: Andreas Feininger from Black Star, Graybar Building, New York."
  - 7 miscellaneous photographs of Walt Whitman statue, grave, beach, house, etc., #3829-s. (Box-folder 5:48)
    Verso of each photograph: "Life Photo by Herbert Gehr."
  - The Valley of the Shadow of Death, n.d., 1 print, #3829-w. (Box-folder 5:49)
    Original print by George Innes. See AMsS, Death's Valley. From Harper's Magazine, volume 84, Number 503, April 1892.
  - Walt Whitman Quarterly Review, 1986/1987, 1 item. (Box-folder 5:50)
    Special double issue: Whitman Photographs.
- Series VI: Odds and Ends
  - Wrappers in which Leaves of Grass was housed when acquired by Clifton Waller Barrett. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Wrappers in which Leaves of Grass was housed when acquired by Clifton Waller Barrett. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Wrappers in which Leaves of Grass was housed when acquired by Clifton Waller Barrett. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Unbound copy, Whitman's Manuscripts: Leaves of Grass (1860): a parallel text / edited with notes and introduction by Fredson Bowers-(Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1955).